(サイ)ムダだよ シカマル。
キミも目覚めるんだ。
It's no use.
Shikamaru, you must come
to your senses.
(シカマル)冗談じゃねえ！
Forget it!
I hate to be woken up when
I'm having a good sleep!
俺はな 気持よく寝てるとこを
起こされるのが→
大嫌いなんだよ！
ハァ。
Cloud of Suspicion
(シカマル)４三銀 ３六歩 ４二飛→
Silver-4c, pawn-3f, rook-4b, rook-4h,
４八飛 ３六角 １六歩→
bishop-3f, pawn-1f, pawn-1d,
pawn-2f, king-6b…
１四歩 ２六歩 ６二玉→
King-6h, king-7b, king-7h, silver-6b…
６八玉 ７二玉→
７八玉 ６二銀。
(サイ)ずいぶん頑張るじゃないか。
You're really hanging in there.
並みの忍なら とっくに
音を上げているところだよ。
The average shinobi would
have given up long ago.
I'm busy playing shogi
with past masters.
歴代の名人たちとの対局に
忙しくてね。
I don't have time to get bored.
退屈してる暇なんてねえ。
好きだな キミのそういう強がり。
I like your stubbornness.
将棋から学ぶことは多いぞ。
You can learn a lot from shogi.
No matter what position you're in,
there's always a way out.
どんな局面にも必ず
逆転の筋が残されているしな。
Are you planning on
getting out of this situation?
この状況から逆転する気かい？
それは楽しみだ。
I look forward to seeing that.
なぁ ライターだけでも返してくれよ。
Hey, can you at least
give me back my lighter?
I just can't calm down
without it.
あれがねえと落ち着かねえんだ。
Sure, when you decide to
accept Lord Gengo's beliefs.
シカマルが ゲンゴ様の志を
受け入れる気になったらね。
どうして あんなやつに従うんだ？
Why would you follow
a guy like that?
Let's just say I found
the place where I belong.
僕はただ
自分の居場所を見つけただけさ。
And that wasn't
the Hidden Leaf Village?
木ノ葉は違うってのか？
Weren't you a member of Team 7?
お前は第七班の
一員じゃなかったのかよ？
だったら どうしてナルトが来ない？
Then why didn't Naruto come?
それほど親しくもなかった
キミが来たのは なぜなんだろうね？
You and I aren't close,
so why did you come?
今回の一件
ナルトは何も聞かされちゃいねえ。
Naruto knows nothing
about this situation.
This was all my decision.
全部 俺の判断だ。
Even still, if this had been
Sasuke or Sakura,
だとしても
もしこれが サスケやサクラだったら→
ナルトが来たんじゃないのかな？
surely Naruto would have come…
I bet Gengo put those ideas
in your head, right?
どうせ その考えも
ゲンゴに吹き込まれたんだろ？
ゲンゴが言葉で人を操ってるのは
間違いねえ。
There's no doubt that
Gengo controls people with words.
So why don't you snap out
of it and wake up?
お前も いいかげん目を覚ませ。
I woke up a long time ago.
目なら とっくに覚めてるよ。
When Lord Gengo gave me a will.
ゲンゴ様に志をいただいたときにね。
フッ…。
Wait.
待てよ。
まだ何か？
Do you still have more to say?
必ず ゲンゴの術を見破って
お前を助けてやるからな。
I promise…
I'm gonna undo Gengo's jutsu
and save you.
そろそろ観念したほうがいい。
I'd resign myself if I were you.
でないと
もっと ひどいことになるよ。
Otherwise, things will get much worse.
(シカマル)お前は木ノ葉の一員だ。
それを忘れんな！
You're a member of the Hidden Leaf.
Don't forget that!
４五歩 ３三角 ３七桂…。
Pawn-4e, bishop-3c…
Knight-3g…
Nope…
ダメだ
今の手持ちじゃ駒が足りねえ。
I don't have enough pieces right now.
The king's gonna get away.
玉に逃げられちまう。
Ro! Is that you?!
朧 お前か!?
That voice…is it you Lord Shikamaru?
(朧)その声は シカマル殿でござるか？
Hey Gengo!
おいゲンゴ こいつらは
俺の命令で動いてただけだ。
These guys were just
obeying my orders!
If you're gonna kill someone,
kill me!
やるなら俺だけにしろ。
(朧)うぅ…。
Remember, as long as you live,
there's a chance.
(シカマル)いいか 生きてりゃ
機は必ず来る。
諦めるんじゃねえぞ。
Don't give up!
I won't let you give up and die!
くたばりやがったら
承知しねえからな！
(朧)だ… 大丈夫でござる。
このくらい屁のカッパでござるよ。
Worry not.
This is nothing…
(シカマル)鏃はどうした？
一緒じゃねえのか？
What happened to Soku?
Wasn't she with you?
あいつも無事なんだろ!?
She's okay, isn't she?!
(鏃)あ！
(ゲンゴ)なぜ大名や無能な民どもに
虐げられながら→
Why do you insist on
serving Feudal Lords
and incompetent people
who oppress you?
それでもなお
やつらのために尽くすのだ？
(鏃)お前には関係ないし。
Like, that's none of
your business!
(ゲンゴ)思い出せ
お前を見る民どもの目を。
Remember…
The way that those people
looked at you.
その奥には何が見えた？
What did you see deep
inside their eyes?
(鏃)そんなの 忘れたし。
Like, I don't remember!
(ゲンゴ)そんなはずはない。
Sure, you do.
The truth is, it's stuck to your mind
and won't go away. Isn't that so?
本当は頭にこびりついて
離れないのだろう？
思い出せ
お前を見る やつらの目を。
Remember!
The eyes that looked at you.
The suspicious eyes
that feared me,
あれは私を恐れ 疑い
遠ざけようとする目。
and tried to discriminate against me…
Why must you give your proud and
mighty life for people like that?
(ゲンゴ)そんな
下賤の者どものために→
なにゆえ誇り高きお前が
命をかけねばならぬ？
Why pledge loyalty to those
who hold you in bondage?
なにゆえ
お前を縛る者のために➡
忠義を尽くさねばならぬのだ？
(鏃)あいつらは 私を利用する…。
They are using me.
みんな敵だ。
Everyone is an enemy.
There is nothing to fear.
(ゲンゴ)恐れることはない。
振り向け。
Now, turn.
And accept everything.
すべてを受け入れるのだ。
(鏃)うわぁ～！
A will has just been granted.
今 ここに
志は 授けられた。
(サイ)連れてまいりました ゲンゴ様。
I've brought him, Lord Gengo…
窮屈な思いをさせて すまない。
My apologies for
the inhospitable treatment.
As you know,
I can't let down my guard.
用心を怠るわけには
いかないのでね。
I have no intention
of speaking to you.
てめえと話す気はねえ。
言葉で操ろうって魂胆が
見え見えだぜ。
It's obvious you're trying
to control me with your words.
You're starting to look
like your father.
お父上の面影に
似てきたのではないか？
悪いが 調べさせてもらったよ。
ご家族や友人のこと。
Forgive me, but I looked
into your background.
Your family and friends…
And the fact that
you came here to kill me.
それに貴君が
私を殺しに来たこともね。
Why do you people
keep oppressing us?
貴君らは なぜ我々を虐げるのだ？
When did we do that?
俺たちが いつ虐げた？
This land is feeble.
この国は弱い。
満足な資源もなく→
We barely have natural resources
and the ground is fallow,
作物も育たぬ不毛の地で→
yet we are trying
our hardest to survive. That is all.
ただ必死に
生きのびようとしているだけだ。
Yeah right, all the while
you're gathering up Rogue Ninja…
(シカマル)抜け忍をかき集めといて
よく言うぜ！
目的は何だ？
戦争でも始めようってのか？
What's your motive?
Are you planning on starting a war?
I'm not gathering them.
集めているのではない。
彼らのほうから救いを求めて
集まってくるのだ。
They come to me,
seeking salvation.
救いだと？
Salvation?!
Have you never questioned
the current existence of shinobi?
貴君は今の忍のあり方に
疑問を持ったことはないか？
戦もせず 大名や金持ちどもの
走狗に甘んじる。
Without war,
they are no more than hunting dogs
for Feudal Lords and the rich.
それで真の忍といえるだろうか？
Is that truly a fitting life
for a shinobi?
何が言いてえ？
What is it that
you're trying to say?
They come here because
they want to be real shinobi.
この国に集まってくる者たちは→
皆 忍らしくありたいと
願っているだけだ。
連合は やみくもに
平和を求めるあまり→
The alliance of nations
to maintain a dark peace…
忍を無意味な掟で縛るばかり。
and bind shinobi with
meaningless laws.
だが そこから
はみ出す人間は必ず出てくる。
But there will always
be those who reject it.
This land is merely
the gathering place for them.
この国は その受け皿に
なっているにすぎぬ！
平和を維持するためには
多少のルールは必要だ！
Various rules are necessary
to preserve peace.
貴君のいう平和とは
すべて 大国が押し付ける理屈だ。
The peace you speak of
is nothing but a theory,
forced upon us
by the Great Nations.
その証拠に貴君らは
尾獣を有している。
The Tailed Beasts that
you keep are proof of that.
Had you used one,
もしも あれを使われたら
この国など ひとたまりもない。
this land would be
completely helpless.
違うかね？
Isn't that so?
We have no intention of ever using
a Tailed Beast for war again.
俺たちは 二度と 尾獣を
戦に使うつもりなんかねえ。
You keep the Tailed Beast
to yourselves,
自分たちだけ
尾獣を所有しておいて→
and you expect us to believe that?
我々に その言葉を
信じろというのか？
Isn't that the biggest excuse
by the Great Nations?
それが大国の理屈でなくて
なんなのだ？
勝手に決めてんじゃねえよ！
ならば どうだ？
Quit jumping to conclusions.
Then how about this?
この国にも尾獣をくれぬか？
Give this land a Tailed Beast too.
たしか雲隠れの里に
一匹残っていたな。
I'm sure the Hidden Cloud
has an extra one, correct?
そうすれば 我々も安心して
貴君らのことを信じよう。
Then we wouldn't worry,
and we would believe you.
You know we can't do that.
んなこと できっこねえだろ！
そうだろうとも。
Of course not.
口先では平和を唱えながら
結局のところ貴君らは→
You espouse peace openly…
but deep down, you don't trust
small countries like ours.
我々のような小国のことなど
信用していないのだからな！
But you can't make the argument
for war because of that.
だからって戦をしていいっていう
理屈にはならねえ！
他にも解決策はあるはずだ！
There's got to be another solution.
他の解決策か…。
You need another solution?
Come with me.
来たまえ。
貴君に見せたいものがある。
I'd like to show you something…
ここは…。
What is this?
標高の高い この里では
作物も ろくに育たない。
Agricultural crops can't grow
at our elevation.
人々の生活の糧はなく
貧しさに あえぐばかりだ。
The people live in poverty
with little to eat.
せめて 何か物産品があれば
生活の足しになる。
If we just had some kind
of product,
something to add value
to their lives…
そう考えて
品種改良で作ったのが この花だ。
This flower is the result
of selective breeding.
貴君も あちこちで
目にしたのではないかな？
You've seen it here and there,
haven't you?
しかし ムダだったよ。
But it was all for nothing…
この花は 里から出したとたんに
枯れてしまう。
This flower wilts the moment
it's taken out of this village,
due to its unique environment.
この里の環境は特殊なのだ。
貴君は どうして
忍の道を目指した？
Why did you choose
the way of the shinobi?
書類整理をするためか？
さぁな。
Was it to file away documents
for the rest of your life?
Who knows.
おそらくは違うはずだ。
Most likely not.
日々 忍の腕を磨き
己を鍛え上げる。
You train daily to hone
your skills.
そして その技をもって 敵を倒し
大切なものを守る。
And with your skills,
you defeat the enemy,
to protect what is precious.
That is the way a shinobi
should live.
それこそが忍らしい生き方だ。
That is the way your father
and mentor lived.
かつて お父上や恩師が
そうしたようにな。
てめえに 何がわかる！
How would you know?!
貴君とて いずれ 彼らに
肩を並べたいと思わぬはずがない。
You probably hope that you can
measure up to them someday.
しかし
ただ平和なだけの世の中で→
But in a world of peace,
can you really accomplish that?
果たして それが
成し得るだろうか？
戦があったからこそ 忍の技術は
めざましい発展を遂げたのだ。
It is because of war,
that shinobi abilities underwent
remarkable development.
もし 平和が続いていたら→
If there had been continual peace,
even you would never have spent
such worthwhile moments with your friends.
今の貴君も
友と過ごした価値ある時間も→
すべて 得られなかったはずだ。
違うかね？
Am I wrong?
それが 平和の代償なら
俺は喜んで 武器を置く！
If that's the price for peace,
I'll gladly throw down my weapons.
それは本心ではない。
You're not speaking
from your heart.
(シカマルの声)お前自身 腕の衰えを
感じているんだろう？
You feel your own abilities
weakening, don't you?
シカマル君。
Shikamaru…
その口を閉じろ！
Shut up!
手を出すな。
Stay out of this.
恐れることはない シカマルよ。
Do not fear, Shikamaru.
さぁ その手を下ろしなさい。
Put your hand down.
そうだ それでいい。
Yes, that's it.
まずは 落ち着こうじゃないか。
深呼吸してみたまえ。
First, why don't you calm down?
Take a deep breath.
どうだね？
私の自慢の花の香りは。
Do you like it?
The scent of my precious flowers?
さぁ。
Come on.
I get it…
なるほど… そういうわけか。
So, that's it.
ある種の花の香りには
思い出を呼び覚ます薬効がある。
The scent of certain flowers has
the effect of stirring up memories.
てめえは それを
洗脳に利用したってわけだ。
So, that's what you've been
using to brainwash people.
とんだ志だぜ！
What inconceivable will…
それに気づいたところで
どうにもなるまい。
But that discovery won't
get you anywhere.
私に逆らうことなどできぬ。
You cannot disobey me.
Where are my comrades?!
Where are Ro and Soku?!
俺の仲間は… 朧と鏃は どこだ!?
ここへ連れてこい！
Bring them here!
We are right here.
(朧)もう来ているでござる。
あぁっ！ お前ら!!
Huh?! You two?!
(鏃)私たちは
ゲンゴ様に志をいただいたんだし。
Like, Lord Gengo has
given us the will...
捜せ！ やつをこの城から出すな!!
Find him! Don't let him escape
from this castle!
シカマル… 隠れても ムダだよ。
Shikamaru, it's useless to hide.
うぅ… まだ痺れてやがる。
I'm still numb…
Damn it, Soku!
鏃のやつめ！
影は使えねえ。 飛車角も取られた。
状況は かんばしくねえな…。
I can't use my Shadows.
My rook and bishop two-piece
handicap is gone too.
The situation is bleak.
It's unlike you…
((シカマル : 珍しいっすね
いきなり棒銀なんて。
I can't believe you'd go
with the Climbing Silver.
(アスマ)敵陣突破の先兵だ。
It's using an advance unit
to break through enemy lines.
(たまには
こういう指し方もできねえとな))
You have to be ready to use tactics
like this once in a while…
ここで逃げたら
木ノ葉のリスクが高まる…。
If I escape now, the risk for
the Hidden Leaf will increase.
That's what you told me back then.
あんた あんとき そう言ったよな。
So, I guess that time
has come for me.
俺にも
そのときが来たってことなのか。
落ち着け。 まだ
逆転の筋は残されてるはずだ。
Calm down.
There's still a chance
an opportunity will present itself.
((アスマ : シカマル…
さしずめ お前は桂馬だな))
Shikamaru, presently,
you are the knight.
敵陣突破の棒銀か
それとも 桂馬の高跳びか。
Breaking through the enemy camp
with a Climbing Silver or…
perhaps a knight that jumps high…
ここは もういっぺん
玉の懐に飛び込むしかねえか。
Guess I have no choice
but to jump back into
the den of the king.
(朧)ゲンゴ様…
シカマル捜しを サイ殿に任せきりで→
Lord Gengo, are you sure
it's all right
to leave the search
for Shikamaru to Sai?
よろしいのでござるか？
Like, it will be bad is
he gets out of the castle.
(鏃)城の外に逃げられたら
面倒だし。
Don't panic.
(ゲンゴ)慌てるな。
彼は追い込まれれば
追い込まれるほど→
If he gets cornered,
he's the type
あえて 困難な状況に身を投じる…
そういう男だ。
to throw himself into an even
more difficult situation.
そうだな？ シカマル。
Isn't that right, Shikamaru?
気づいてたのかよ
つまんねえな。
You knew I was here?
That's no fun.
貴君が これを
残していくはずはないしな。
You wouldn't leave this behind.
わざわざ戻ってくるなんて
おめでたいやつだし。
You came back just for that?
You're something.
おとなしく捕まるでござる！
Resign yourself
and be captured!
床がダメなら
天井って手もあるんだぜ！
If the floor won't work,
there's always the ceiling.
(朧)下でござる！
Below.
うっ 体が…。
My body…
おっと！
シカマル殿 はなすでござる！
Whoa…
Lord Shikamaru, release me!
幻術を解くには
かけた人間を倒すのがセオリーだが→
To break a genjutsu,
the theory is to bring down
the one who placed it.
そこんとこは どうなんだ ゲンゴ？
What do you say, Gengo?
Impossible.
ムダだ 私の言葉に
抗うことなどできぬ。
No one can resist my words.
朧 悪いが しばらく
俺の盾になってもらうぜ。
Ro…
Sorry, but you'll have to
be my shield for a while.
撃て！
朧に当たっても構わぬ。
Shoot.
Don't worry about hitting Ro.
撃ってみな
ただし よく狙ってな。
Go ahead and shoot.
Just make sure you aim straight.
シカマル 止まれ！
私の声には逆らえぬ！
Stop, Shikamaru.
You cannot resist my voice.
キサマ まさか…。
Don't tell me you—?!
鏃の攻撃を
わざと耳に受け→
You purposely let Soku
hit you in the ear
一時的に聴覚を麻痺させたのか？
to dull your sense of hearing?!
これが桂馬の高跳びだ！
This is the knight's jump!
うわ！
惜しいな シカマル。
実に惜しい。
I'm disappointed, Shikamaru.
So disappointed.
ゲンゴ様は奥へ。
ここは私にお任せください。
Please stay back, Lord Gengo.
Leave this to me.
よくやった。
(シカマル)ゲンゴ！
Well done!
Gengo!
逃がしはせぬ！
You won't get away!
しまった！
Damn it!
((シカク : ったく てめえは女の子に
やられてばかりだな。
Damn it, you keep
getting beaten up by girls.
仲間のため てめえがより優秀に
なるんじゃなかったのかよ？
Weren't you going to
become a better leader
for the sake of your comrades?
(シカマル)親父 俺はさ
やっぱ忍には向いてねえんだよ。
Dad… I…
I'm just not cut out to
be a shinobi.
(はあ…))
(朧)死んだでござるか？
Is he dead?
(鏃)まだ殺してはいないし。
I didn't like, kill him yet.
まあ 最後は
やぶれかぶれでござったな。
Well, he had no chance
at the end.
(サイ)哀れなものだね。
How pitiful…
《体も限界だ
空気もやけに重いぜ。
I'm physically at my limit.
The air feels so heavy.
なんかもう めんどくせえ》
Man, this is such a drag.
(チョウジ)シカマル 大丈夫？
Are you okay, Shikamaru?
(いの)死んだら
承知しないからね？
Don't you dare die on us!
ヒヒヒ。
ウフ。
お前ら… っつか
どうしてここに？
You guys?!
But what're you doing here?
そっか 俺は まだ夢を…。
Oh, I get it. I'm still dreaming…
(テマリ)シカマル！
テ テマリ！
Shikamaru!
T-Temari?!
お前は 私が見込んだ男だろう？
I expect a lot more from you!
何ボサッとしてんだよ！
Why're you just sitting around
dazed like that?!
シカマル！
やめてよ テマリ！
Shikamaru?!
Stop it, Temari!
本当に死んじゃうってば。
黙ってろ！
He'll really die.
Shut up!
今のは 連合の会議で
私にウソをついた分だ。
That's for lying to me at
the Allied Forces meeting.
(シカマル)すまなかったな テマリ。
え？
Sorry, Temari.
おかげで目が覚めたぜ。
Thanks to you,
I've come to my senses.
シカマル。
悪いがここ頼めるか？
Shikamaru!
Sorry, but can you take over here?
倒さなきゃならない相手が
もう１人いるんだ。
I have one more guy
to take down.
ゲンゴだろ？
Is that Gengo?!
どうして それを？
火影様に聞いたんだ。
How did you know?
Lord Hokage told me.
聞き出すのには
ちょっと苦労したけどね。
I had a hell of a time trying
to get it out of him.
どうやって聞き出したかは
あんまし想像したくねえな。
I don't want to
even imagine what you did.
シカマル こいつら
倒しちゃっていいんだよね？
So, Shikamaru, it's okay
to crush these guys?
洗脳されてはいるが
２人とも仲間だ。
They're brainwashed,
but they're comrades.
そいつらも
目を覚まさせてやってくれ。
Please wake them up as well!
言ってくれるし！
待て！
Like, shut your mouth.
Wait!
え？
もう１つ 忘れ物だぞ！
You're forgetting one thing.
向こうも
お前が来るのを見越して➡
He probably knows you're coming
and has laid traps.
罠を張っているはずだ。
その体で勝算はあるんだろうな？
I hope the odds of your winning
in that condition is good.
捨て駒になるつもりはねえ。
I have no intention of being
a sacrificial pawn.
なら よし！
All right then!
さて サシの勝負といこうか。
Okay, let's get on with our final moves…
ゲンゴ！
Gengo!
TO BE CONTINUED
The Hidden Leaf still holds
that much importance to you?
Damn right!
Then I'll let you in
on something good…
What would you think if I said
I've sent my comrades